Guide to the Carole De Saram Papers 1972-2011 MS 3059
New-York Historical Society
- Series 1: Subject Files, 1972-2011; 10 Linear feet and 1 over-size folder
  - Tweed Courthouse Library Request, 1984-1985 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
    The City budgeted $36 million for rehabilitation of the landmark Tweed Court House in fiscal year 1985-1986. This folder contains correspondence regarding a proposal from the New York Public Library to reserve some space in the Tweed Court House for a downtown library branch. Community Board #1 and the TCA supported this proposal, which was turned down by the Mayor's office.
  - Tax Cuts and Incentives, 1993-2006 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
    De Saram's notes read: "Public Properties, Development Rights, and Inclusionary Housing Program."
  - Lower Manhattan Rezoning Maps (1 of 2 folders), 1991-1999 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
  - Lower Manhattan Rezoning Maps (2 of 2 folders) over-size, 1991-1999 (Box over-size small)
    One "Hudson Square, Trinity Real Estate Map of Tribeca". One enlarged map of Tribeca which includes building names and lot numbers.
  - Lower Manhattan Photos (1 of 2 folders), 2005, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
    Includes photgraphs of: 4 Leonard Street, 53 Chambers Street, 54 Chambers Street 182 Duane Street, NW corner of Frankin and Varick, SE corner of Duane and Greenwich Streets, 34 North Moore Street, Tribeca Upholstery storefront, and Pelavin Editions storefront.
  - Lower Manhattan Photos (2 of 2 folders) over-size, 1991-1999 (Box over-size small)
    Two photographs. One aerial view of Tribeca blocks bound by West St, Hudson St, Clarkson and Canal Sts. One street view looking west captioned, "Sanitation parking cars illegally on street."
  - Noho Rezoning: A Discussion Paper, 2002 August (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
    Prepared for Friends of NoHo Architecture. Prepared by Buckhurst Fish & Jacquemart Inc.
  - Traffic Studies, Sanitation Garage & Salt Facility, and Realize Hudson Rise Alternative Plan (Box -, Folder -)
  - DSNY Garage - Notices, Proposals, Statements, and Legal Documents, 1999-2008 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
    Original folder reads: "Department of Sanitation Garbage Truck Garage Documents."
  - DSNY Garage - Letters, Notices, and Flyers, 1994-2009 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7-8)
    Original folder reads: "Department of Sanitation Garbage Truck Garage - Letters, City Board, City Officials, Public Hearings. $429 Million."
  - DSNY Garage - North of Canal to Spring Street, 1990-2008 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9)
    Original folder reads: "600 Washington St, 505 Greenwich St, 491 Greenwich St, Between Canal and Spring Sts."
  - DSNY Garage - Press, Saatchi & Saatchi Event, 2007-2009 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 10)
    Original folder reads: "Department of Sanitation Garage for Garbage Trucks, Press. $429 million. Saatchi & Saatchi Event, Laurie Anderson, Lou Reed, James Gandolfini."
  - DSNY Garage - "Hudson Rise" Alternative Plan, 2008-2009 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 10)
    Original folder reads: "Department of Sanitation Garage - Community Solution. 'Hudson Rise' Alternative Plan, Z & H Architects."
  - Zoning Regulations, 2003-2004 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11)
    Zoning Resolutions published by the City of New York including: Article II - Residence District Regulations, Article III - Commericial District Regulations, Article IV - Maunfacturing District Regulations, and Article XI - Special Purpose Districts - Chapter 1: Special Tribeca Mixed Use District.
  - 55 White Street, 1986-1992 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
    Original folder reads: "Battle led to making Tribeca an historic district. Would have demolished a 5 story synagogue at 49 White Street."
  - Duane Hotel, 2000-2003 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
    Original folder reads: "Duane Hotel aka Southwest Corner of 188 Church Street and 130-132 Duane Street."
  - Hudson River Trust, Friends of Hudson River Park, Pier 40, 1982-2009 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
  - Envisioning Hudson Square booklet, 2007 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
    Architectural Design Charrette. Project Director: Michael Kramer. Curator: Stella Kramer
  - Canal Street, 1983-2001 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15)
    Original folder reads: "Canal Street Corridor, Congestion, Mitigation, and Air Quality (CMAQ). Sponsors: Council member Kathryn Freed, Richard Barrett (CWC), Carole De Saram (TCA). Canal Street & Washington Street Intersection. Canal Street Intersection Photos and Papers."
  - Hudson River and Route 9A Development (Box -, Folder -)
    De Saram's notes read: "Waterfront, 197A, Battery Park City, NY-NJ Harbor, Lower Broadway, Westside Highway Replacement Study."
  - Waterfront / 9A - Letters, Notices, Flyers, and Press, 1980-2007 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Battery Park City Plan, West Side Light Rail - Letters, Notices, Flyers, and Press, 1982-1990 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
  - Manhattan Valley Circulation Study, 1986 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
    Original folder reads: "Socioeconomic Profile, NYC Transit Authority Council - Light Rail Line on Westside."
  - New York - New Jersey Harbor Estuary Program / The River Project, 1988-1989 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
  - Lower Broadway Corridor Study, Alternative City Task Force, and 197C Remapping Application, 1986-1993 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5)
  - Tribeca Community Association Quality of Life Issues - Lawsuits (Box -, Folder -)
  - Project Return Foundation - Drug Treatment Center, 1988-1992 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
    The Project Return files document a proposed residential and outpatient drug treatment center slated for 107-113 Franklin Street in Tribeca that was to be funded by the State Division of Substance Abuse Services and managed by the Project Return Foundation. The Tribeca Community Association was strongly opposed to this facility in their neighborhood and activated the community in petitioning against it. In 1991, the Division of Substance Abuse Services announced they would not provide the $6.3 million funding for the project, citing the fiscal crisis as the reason for their withdrawl.
  - Project Return - Letters, Press Releases, 1988-1992 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6-8)
  - Manhattan Neighborhood Council, 1994-1997 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
    Original folder reads: "Formed against social service facilities. Conflict of interest on City Boards. Community facilities placements. 500 people from all areas of the city attended the first meeting." This folder documents the steps taken by the Manhattan Neighborhood Council and the Mayor's Office to reconcile reports of conflicts of interest on community boards where members were allegedly using their public positions to benefit their private interests.
  - Westway Canal - Toxic Waste Plant and Microwave Pollution, 1984 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
  - Stonewall Play - Debrosses and Watts Streets, 1994 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
  - Helicopter Noise Safety, 1995-2000 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
  - Quality of Life Issues, 1994-1999 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
    Original folder reads: "Movie house - North Moore Street. TCA filed suit against City Planning. Developers dropped plans for movie house. Franklin Street Cleaners - use of toxins. Duane Street Cleaners - use of toxins. John Kennedy Jr. attended CB#1 meetings against cleaners and testified at both hearings.
  - NYS Parole Board - Letters, Press, Flyers, 1980-1982 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 10-11)
    This file documents responses from the Tribeca community after hearing that the State Parole Board was planning on relocating their office to 21-25 Hudson Street. The South of Canal Association (SOCA) was formed in January 1982 as a result of widespread opposition to the Parole Board office relocation and worked with Community Board #1 to prevent the planned move. In March 1982, the Parole Board withdrew the plans to relocate to Hudson Street following negotiations with the Department of City Planning, the Manhattan Borough President, and other city officials.
  - Khapra Beetle Attack - USDA Fumigation (1 of 2), 1982-2005 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 12)
    The Khapra beetle attack - USDA fumigation refers to the extermination procedure overseen by the USDA when the Port Warehouse, located at 47 Vestry Street, was wrapped in tarpaulin and pumped with methyl bromide gas on 11 November 1982. The USDA had hired a fumigation company from Florida and the neighborhood was not given adequate notice of the planned use of this toxic, odorless gas. De Saram and CB#1 held an emergency meeting with government agencies present and were able to postpone the fumigation for a few weeks to notify neighbors and put hospitals on alert. Following the event, CB#1 organized an all-day conference on "The Use of Toxins in an Urban Environment". Field experts, government agencies, and the USDA participated.
  - Khapra Beetle Attack - USDA Fumigation (2 of 2), 1982-2005 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
    The press packet for "The Use of Toxins in an Urban Environment" conference, is included in this file.
  - Nightlife, Discos, and Bars - Letters, Notices, Flyers, and Press, 1979-2008 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2-8)
    Topics covered include noise codes and the Noise Task Force, nightclub violence and police reports, incident complaints from residents, the State Liquor Authority and liquor licenses, rooftop zoning, the Manhattan Borough President's Nightlife Task Force, Club Vinyl aka Wetlands Preserve, and brothels.
  - Tribeca Parks Founded by Community (Box -, Folder -)
  - Finn Square, 1985-1990 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 9-10)
    This file includes letters, grant applications, meeting minutes, and notices regarding sponsorship and renovation of Finn Square.
  - Bogardus Park, 1987-2011 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 11-12)
    Includes letters, notices, flyers, minutes, press, financial statements, and petitions, regarding the designation of space at the intersection of Hudson, Reade, West Broadway, and Chambers Streets, as James Bogardus Triangle. James Bogardus is known as "the father of Cast-Iron Architecture." The Tribeca Community Association and Friends of Bogardus Triangle, with support from Friends of Cast Iron Architecture, obtained State and Federal funds, hired an architect, and worked with area residents and businesses to design a viewing garden in this location that was once just concrete and a few trees.
  - Bogardus Park, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    One additional letter added to the collection by De Saram in 2021 and boxed separately.
  - Shearson Park, 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 13)
    Shearson Park refers to the 23,000-square-foot plaza next to the Shearson Lehman Brothers/American Express building at 390 Greenwich Ave. The park opened in 1986 on an interim basis as part of a community amenity provided by the company in exchange for approval of its project by the Board of Estimate in 1984. On 25 June 25th, 1987, three quarters of the plaza was bulldozed and fenced off in preparation for the construction of a new 40-story office tower. Four neighborhood civic associations, including the TCA, and four residents of Lower Manhattan filed a case against Shearson/AMEX calling for the green park space to be restored.
  - Canal Street Park, 1998-2008 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 13)
    This file contains notices, letters, press, images, and ephemera related to the reconstruction of Canal Park by community groups including the Tribeca Community Association and the Canal West Coalition. Canal Park was used as a public square in the early 19th century and was redesigned by Calvert Vaux and Samuel Parsons, Jr. in 1888. After the ground-breaking ceremony for the Holland Tunnel in 1920, the park became a construction site, followed by a parking lot for the remainder of the 20th century. In 1998, Tribeca community groups joined together to compile research, obtain funding, and petition the city for the park to be reconstituted as Vaux and Parsons had designed it.
  - Greening of Greenwich, 1988-2004 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 14)
    This file contains letters, press, resolutions, and a scope of service related to the Greening of Greenwich Project, which was fulfilled in December 2000. This community driven project sought to narrow the wider portion of Greenwich Street to provide more space for greenery and pedestrian traffic.
  - Washington Market Park, 1980-2006 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 14)
    This file includes letters, memorandum, press, and newsletters related to the interim-site reserved for Washington Market Community Park, near Independence Plaza, during the early 1980s when Manhattan Community College resumed campus building construction. With the help of Assemblyman Paul Viggiano, the park was preserved and made a permanent community fixture. Other topics include concerns from Friends of Washington Market Park regarding surrounding traffic and development in the 2000s. There is a DVD containing a 6 minute documentary detailing the traffic dangers at Duane and Greenwich Streets. The video was made by Friends of Washington Market Park with The Streets Renaissance Project. This DVD is restricted within the collection due to preservation issues.
  - Duane Park, 1984, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 14)
    Small amount of material related to the activities of Friends of Duane Park.
  - Tribeca Open Space Study by Susan Mareneck, 1992 June (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1)
  - Parks Department, 2000-2004 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1)
    This file contains promotional material, brochures, 9th Annual State of the Parks Address dated January 18th, 2002, and a press article
  - Texture of Tribeca Book (Box -, Folder -)
    "The Texture of Tribeca" is a book written by Andrew Dolkart, published in 1989. This book was instrumental in raising awareness about the history of Tribeca and acheiving landmark status. These files document the TCA's efforts to raise money for the book through organized benefit events. Successful silent auctions were made possible by art and service donations from Tribeca artists and business owners.
  - Benefits (3 of 4 folders), 1986-1995 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 2-4)
    Original folder reads: "To raise money to print 'Texture of Tribeca', house tours, walking tours with Andrew Dolkart (12/13/93 and 6/11/95), art auctions" File includes artist description and donation forms, letters, press releases, TCA committee and volunteer lists, and ephemera.
  - Benefits (4 of 4 folders) over-size, 1986-1995 (Box over-size small)
    "Tribeca Alert!" poster publicizing the Tribeca Benefit Art Auction featuring artwork by Mimi Gross.
  - Andrew Dolkart, 1988-2002 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 4)
    Author of "Texture of Tribeca".
  - Miscellaneous Photos and Lithographs, [Images] (1 of 3 folders), undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 5)
    Includes magazine pages, photographs, photocopies, and printouts of Tribeca buildings and streetviews, some in color. Many of the images are annotated by De Saram in the margins. Portrayed buildings and addresses include: 54 Laight Street, 50 Duane Street, 165 Duane Street, 55 White Street, the Cary Building, and Independence Plaza North Apartments.
  - Miscellaneous Photos and Lithographs, [Images] (2 of 3 folders) over-size, 1989 September (Box over-size small)
    "Times in Tribeca" article in Metropolis with black and white images of Tribeca views.
  - Miscellaneous Photos and Lithographs, [Images] (3 of 3 folders) over-size (Box over-size small)
    "Perspectives on the Manhattan Civic Center", designed and curated by the Municipal Art Society Fellows Committee on Preservation and Urbanism. (black and white printout copy)
  - Untitled [Correspondence, Press, Ephemera] (1 of 2 folders), 1984-1995 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6)
    Includes invitations for book publication celebrations and an advertisement for the book among correspondence and press articles related to "The Texture of Tribeca."
  - Untitled [Correspondence, Press, Ephemera] (2 of 2 folders) over-size, 1984-1995 (Box over-size small)
    "The Texture of Tribeca" black and white poster advertising the book
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Assignments for Tribeca Research and Photo Volunteers, 1984-1985 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6)
  - The Committee for the Washington Market Historic District - Informational Packet, 1986-1988 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6)
  - Tribeca Community Association (TCA) Papers (Box -, Folder -)
    Contains internal organizational records about the Tribeca Community Association and Community Board #1.
  - Tribeca Press, 1972-2009 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - TCA Letters, Newsletters, Notices, and Meetings, 1984-2007 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 9)
  - TCA Grants, 1985-1992 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 10)
  - TCA Organizational Information, 1984-2010 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 11)
    Original folders read: "TCA description, bylaws, IRS 4T (1/29/87), charities registration and receipt, certificate of incorporation, NYS letter of incorporation, NYS filing receipt, NYS letters of certificate of incorporation. Carole De Saram - CB#1 appointment, [with] Mayor [at] Gracie Mansion, Parks Commissioner, City Journal. TCA Incorporation - State and Federal, 1986 filed, 1987 approved."
  - Community Board #1 (CB#1) (1 of 2 folders), 1978-2007 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 12)
    Original folders read: "CB#1 applicants, variances, lawsuits, demos. CB#1 audit. CB#1 letters and members."
  - Community Board #1 (CB#1) (2 of 2 folders) over-size, 1978-2007 (Box over-size small)
    "Where Particular People Congregate" parliamentary procedures at a glance, printed as a community service by the Houston Chronicle.
  - Handbook for Community Board Members, Revised 1992 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 13)
    Published by the City of New York, David N. Dinkins, Mayor, Community Assistance Unit, Office of the Mayor, Michael Kharfen, Director.
  - Carole De Saram - Appointments, 1978-2010 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 13)
    Appointments to CB#1, BMCC Boards, and others. There are letters of endorsement for De Saram from community leaders and politicians. Includes a 5 page personal statement from De Saram depicting her leading roles in the Washington Market Park community project and the USDA Khapra beetle fumigation event. The first Newsletter from CB#1 (Issue I, Number 1) is also present, dated April-June, 1978.
  - CB#1 Resolutions and Zoning Letters, 1979-2008 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 14)
  - "416-424 Washington Street, New York, New York: A Study of a Particular Site and General Preservation Design Ethics in the United States." By: Laura Patricia Brugger, 1994 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirement for the degree Master of Science in Historic Preservation. Graduate School of Architecture, Planning and Preservation, Columbia University.
  - Photographs (Box -, Folder -)
  - Photographs (Folder 1 of 4), circa 2000? (Offsite-box 11, Folder 13)
    Photos from North Tribeca. Include, among others, the area of 504-506 Canal, rear of 508 Canal, corner of Canal and Greenwich, 530 Canal, 288 West, Watts and Washington, Desbrosses and Washington.
  - Photographs (Folder 2 of 4), circa 2000? (Offsite-box 11, Folder 14)
    Photos from North Tribeca. Include, among others, corner Washington and Desbrosses, Washington and Watts, 459-465 Washington.
  - Photographs (Folder 3 of 4), circa 2000? (Offsite-box 11, Folder 15)
    Photos from North Tribeca. Include, among others, 466 Washington, Vestry and Watts, various places along Greenwich.
  - Photographs (Folder 4 of 4), circa 2000? (Offsite-box 11, Folder 16)
    14 photos from East and South Tribeca.
- Series 2: Publications, 1974-2009; 1 Linear feet
  Series II consists of publications such as booklets, guides, pamphlets, brochures, ephemera, periodicals, manuals and reports.
  The Publications series is arranged alphabetically by title except for smaller pamphlets, guides, and ephemera, which are arranged by subject content.
  - 1990 Annual Report. Committee on Environmental Conservation. Maurice D. Hinchey, Chairman; Mel Miller, Speaker. New York State Assembly., 1990 December 15 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
  - The ABC (and C2, and M3, and R10A) of Zoning. CIVITAS' Upper East Side/Harlem Guide. Text and Illustrations: Jack Huberman. Design: Jennifer Clark Design, Inc., NYC., 1991 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
  - "American Express" Its Origin and Growth by Ralph T. Reed; Member of the Newcomen Society, President of the American Express Company, New York., 1952 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
  - Biennial Report. City of New York Parks & Recreation., 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Brooklyn Bridge: The Official Illustrated History by Richard Rodin. Brooklyn Bridge Centennial Celebration 1883-1983. (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
  - Critical Issues Critical Choices: A Mobility Plan for the New York Region Through the Year 2015. Published by the New York Metropolitan Transportation Council., 1994-1996 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
    Includes the Executive Summary and "We are a Region!" Report.
  - End of the Road for Ladies' Mile? by Margaret Moore., 1986 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
    First presented as a slide lecture at The Municipal Art Society of New York, April 24, 1985.
  - A Fair Land to Build In: The Architecture of the Empire State by Brendan Gill. Published by the Preservation League of New York State, Inc., 1984 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
  - Forty Years of New York City Landmarks Preservation: An Opportunity to Review, Reflect, and Reform. Committee on Governmental Operations, The Council of The City of New York. Hon. Bill Perkins - Chair., August 2005 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
  - The Fragility of Life: The Neighborhoods of New York City. by Michael Winkleman, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Independence Plaza North. Approval and Tax Abatement by Board of Estimate City of New York. Supervised by: The Housing and Development Administration of the City of New York, Roger Starr (Administrator/Commissioner), 1974 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
  - The Livable City: A Publication of the Municipal Art Society. Number 15/1., March 1991 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
  - Location of Plaza Addresses in the Borough of Manhattan, Manhattan Borough President's Office. David N. Dinkins - Borough President, 1987 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
  - Manual for Small Claims Arbitrators: A Comprehensive Guide to Litigating in the Small Claims Part of the Civil Court of the City of New York, Fourth Edition., June 1998 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
    Prepared by: Arthur F. Engoron of The Association of Arbitrators, Small Claims Part, Civil Court of the City of New York.
  - Map Data Catalog, National Mapping Program. Published by the U.S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, National Cartographic Information Center (NCIC), circa 1980s (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
  - The New York Chronicle, Editor: Richard McDermott, 1989-1992 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 4)
    Includes: Vol 3 No 4 Fall 1989, Vol 4 No 1 Winter 1990, Vol 4 No 2 Spring/Summer 1990, Vol 4 No 3 Fall 1990, Vol 4 No 4 Winter/Spring 1991, Vol 5 No 1 Summer 1991, Vol 5 No 2 Fall/Winter 1991, Vol 5 No 3 Spring/Summer 1992, Vol 5 No 4 Fall/Winter 1992.
  - The New York Chronicle, Editor: Richard McDermott, 1993-1996 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
    Includes: Vol 6 No 1 Spring 1993, Vol 6 No 2 Summer 1993, Vol 6 No 3 Fall/Winter 1993, Vol 7 No 1 Summer 1994, Vol 7 No 2 Fall 1994, Vol 8 No 1 Summer 1995, Vol 8 No 2 Fall/Winter 1995, Vol 8 No 3 Winter 1996.
  - New York City Cultural Infrastructure Task Force Report and Recommendations, 1993 November 22 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6)
  - New York City Economic Development Corporation: Taking Business to New Heights Produced by the New York City Economic Development Corporation, 1995 November (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6)
  - New York Magazine, 1978 April 17 and 1989 December 25-1990 January 1 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6)
    Include articles about Tribeca, some annotatated by De Saram.